<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The impostures of seducing teachers discovered; in a sermon before the Right Honorable the Lord Major and court of Aldermen of the city of London, at their anniversary meeting on Tuesday in Easter weeke, April 23, 1644. at Christ-Church. By Richard Vines, minister of Gods word at Weddington in the county of Warwick, and a member of the Assembly of Divines. Imprimatur, Charles Herle.</title>
            <author>Vines, Richard, 1600?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V557</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E48_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11333</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858995</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111056</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95973)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111056)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 9:E48[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The impostures of seducing teachers discovered; in a sermon before the Right Honorable the Lord Major and court of Aldermen of the city of London, at their anniversary meeting on Tuesday in Easter weeke, April 23, 1644. at Christ-Church. By Richard Vines, minister of Gods word at Weddington in the county of Warwick, and a member of the Assembly of Divines. Imprimatur, Charles Herle.</title>
                  <author>Vines, Richard, 1600?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M. for Abel Roper at the signe of the Sunne over against St Dunstans church in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Ephesians IV, 14-15 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111056:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IMPOSTVRES OF Seducing Teachers Diſcovered; In a SERMON before the Right Honourable the LORD MAJOR and Court of ALDERMEN of the City of <hi>London,</hi> at their Anniverſary meeting on Tueſday in Eaſter weeke, <hi>April</hi> 23, 1644. at <hi>Chriſt-Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By RICHARD VINES, Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Weddington</hi> in the County of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> and a Member of the Aſſembly of DIVINES.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>CHARLES HERLE.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 TIM. 2. 17.</bibl> And their word will eate as doth a gangrene.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Abel Roper</hi> at the ſigne of the Sunne over againſt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Dunstans</hi> Church in Fleet-ſtreet, 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111056:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111056:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE LORD MAIOR AND Court of <hi>ALDERMEN,</hi> of the famous Citie of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable and Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Epiſtle Dedicatory uſually beſpeakes a Patron, and then the Reader is epistled afterward. I intreat Readers only and Patrons no further than the Truth may challenge them <hi>ſuo jure.</hi> Though I ſhould have done my ſelfe but right in ſending this Sermon forth into publike, yet your Commands were the ſtronger tye upon me. It was received with ill reſentment by ſome whoſe Character not I but the Apoſtle gives in this Text: the aſpect
<pb facs="tcp:111056:3"/> whereof is (I believe) no more pleaſing than the Sermon; Either they ſhould not weare ſuch faces as are afraid of this glaſſe, or waſh first, and then they will not be angry. I ſhould rejoyce to offend any man for his good, and be afraid to pleaſe him for his hurt; I intended it for a ſtay to the nutant and unstable; a ſtop to that Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene which I hope is not crept ſo neere the Head as to have taken any of you; who in other things have beene ſo farre from being <hi>Children</hi> toſſed to and fro, with windes, ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my winds, that from you posteritie ſhall learne to be <hi>men.</hi> The very holding up of the Text in open view may be a <hi>quo vadis?</hi> to one or other. If not. Yet <hi>Thou haſt delivered thy ſoule,</hi> Ezek. 3. 19, 21. is ſome comfort to him who humbly preſents this Sermon to your hands and eyes, with ſome enlargements here and there, which the time denyed to your eares; and whoſe honour it is to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant for Chriſt, RICHARD VINES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111056:3"/>
            <head>THE IMPOSTVRES OF Seducing Teachers Diſcovered.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EPHES. IV. XIV, XV.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>That we henceforth be no more children, toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the ſleight of men, <hi>and</hi> cunning craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, whereby they lye in wait to deceive.</p>
                  <p>But ſpeaking the truth in love, may grow up into him in all things which is the Head, <hi>even</hi> Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Goſpell had no ſooner aſcended the Horizon of the Gentiles, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel'd that univerſall ſhade wherein they had been benighted, but the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill erected his factories in thoſe new diſcoveries to intercept the trade of truth, therefore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111056:4"/> is our Apoſtle in many of his Epiſtles, ſo much in fortifying beleevers againſt the impreſſions of ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing teachers, and the hyſtorie of <note n="a" place="margin">Fatemur qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem novas quaſdam &amp; antea non au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ectas, Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baptiſtas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inos, Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonios Zwenk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anos ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ad exortum Evangelij ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, <hi>Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> Apol. Eccle. Anglicanae. Vide <hi>Sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarijs.</note> 
               <hi>Luthers</hi> time doth witneſſe alſo that it is the lot of reformations while they are greene and recent, to be infeſted with ſuch ſects and doctrines as haply were never before heard of, and therefore it concernes all to be carefull what money they take when the markets are ſo full of adulterate coyne, and to be armed againſt the ſcandall thence ariſing, as if the truth was the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſuch monſters which are none of hers, but are laid at her doore to bring her into diſcredit; we muſt expect no leſſe, nay haply we have hereby an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the truth is at the threſhold, for it is not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary that tares grow any where but in the wheate field. The Text too fitly ſerves our own meridian, being purpoſely choſen to give antidote againſt the infection of ſeducing teachers.</p>
            <p>Whether the word <hi>Henceforth</hi> doe look back to the time paſt, and imply that the <hi>Epheſians</hi> had been like children toſſed to and fro, as is generally conceived by the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Chryſoſt. Theophilact. Oecumenius, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Greeke expoſitors and others, I ſhall neither enquire nor inſiſt upon it, but ſhall take it as a reſult from what the Apoſtle had ſaid in the beginning of the Chapter, where having in the 4, 5, 6, verſes, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſeven <hi>ones, one body and one ſpirit, one hope of your calling, one Lord, one faith, one baptiſme, one God and Father of all,</hi> wherein the <hi>Epheſians</hi> and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are concenterated. He paſſeth on and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon gifts and miniſteries given to the Church by Jeſus Chriſt, ſitting at the right-hand of God; in which forme of expreſſion he ſeemes to allude to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111056:4"/> the <note n="c" place="margin">As he doth elſewhere, <hi>viz. Luk.</hi> 2. 15. and to the Olympick ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 24, 25, &amp;c. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Romans</hi> in their tryumphs, wherein the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour having the glorious Captaines at his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, ſcattered his munificence in congiaries and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natives to the ſouldiery and people, for ſo our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour <hi>aſcended up on high, and led captivity captive, and gave gifts to men;</hi> and what are thoſe gifts which might become the magnificence of a Conquerour ſo triumphant? are they not miniſteries? ver. 12. <hi>He gave ſome Apostles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, and ſome Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ours and Teachers,</hi> a royall dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive given in the day of his triumph: but the uſe and end whereunto theſe miniſteries are ſubſervient and inſtrumentall addes value to them, as it is ſet forth, ver. 12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>For the perfecting of the Saints,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That we henceforth be no more children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Text you have A Character, and An Antidote. The character is of 2. ſorts of perſons The Seduced, The Seducer.</p>
            <p>The Seduced are called <hi>children toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Seducers are ſaid to be ſleighty, crafty, and to have their artifices, methods, ſtratagems of decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>by the ſleight of men and cunning craftineſſe, whereby they lye in wait to deceive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Antidote or preſervative is two-fold;</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Miniſtery which Chriſt hath given to his Church, <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles,</hi> &amp;c. That henceforth we be no more children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the ſalt (<hi>yee are</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>the ſalt of the earth</hi>) ſerves to preſerve the people from being flye-blowne with every
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111056:5"/> corrupt doctrine unto putrefaction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The holding faſt of the ſubſtance and vitals of practick godlineſſe, ver 15. <hi>Following the truth in love, grow up in all things into him which is the Head</hi> even <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The fortifying of the vitalls is a repercuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to all infections from the ſtinking breath of a currupt teacher.</p>
            <p>I ſhall open each part of the Text as I come to it, And firſt the character or deſcription of the Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, or of them that are unſtable; for there is no doubt but the Apoſtle intends to deſcypher inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and fluctuancy by theſe words, <hi>Children toſsed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;</hi> which is a ſentence (as every eye may ſee) carried on in metaphors and figurative expreſſions, only ſome criticks might haply aske what decorum of ſpeech there is in children toſſed to and fro and carried about with winds? for had it not been more congruity to have ſaid <hi>waves</hi> toſſed to and fro, or <hi>cloudes</hi> carried about, than <hi>children?</hi> but we muſt not teach the Spirit of God to ſpeake, the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſence is obvious and proper; for the better rendering whereof we may conſider;</p>
            <p n="1">1. By what name unſtable people are called, <hi>children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. How their inſtability is expreſſed, <hi>Toſſed to and fro and carried about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. What cauſe there is of it, <hi>Every wind of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt, They are <hi>children</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are ſyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, 1 Cor. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. with Heb. 5. 13. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>
               </note>, ſo called, not in reſpect of age, but of knowledge and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 20. be not children <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111056:5"/> but be men: Where <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> perfect and ripe<note place="margin">And ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in veteri Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamento.</hi> Iſa. 3. 4. Prov. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. Ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>
               </note> men of knowledge are oppoſed to children, that is, ungrounded and unskilfull ones, <hi>unskilfull in the word of righteouſneſſe, for he is a babe,</hi> Heb. 5. 13. Such babes the Apoſtle calls <hi>carnall,</hi> though they be in Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1, 2, 3. and oppoſeth them to <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall,</hi> that is perfect or ripe of knowledge and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and you may ſee that ſuch men, that are ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and unballaſt with knowledge, are eaſily car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into envying, ſtrife, factions, one crying up <hi>Paul,</hi> another <hi>Apollo, ver.</hi> 4. yea they become the certaine prey of Sectaries and ſeducers, made prize of by them, as the <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Col. 2. 8.</note> word ſignifies, <hi>Col,</hi> 2. 8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the ſecond, their inſtability is expreſſed in two <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> metaphors, <hi>toſsed to and fro, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout;</hi> the former is drawn from a wave of the ſea (for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a wave) and ſo it denotes an uncertaine man that fluctuates in opinion, and is explained to the full, <hi>Iames 1. 6. a wavering man is like a wave of the ſea, driven with the wind and toſsed.</hi> The latter from a light cloud ſwimming in the ayre, carried about in a circle having no weight in it, and may well be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by that of <hi>Iude</hi> ver. 12. <hi>clouds without water carried about.</hi> Nor wave nor cloud have any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, but are alwayes in motion if any wind be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, you ſhall in vaine look to find them anon where you ſee them now.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the third, The cauſe of this inſtability is <hi>every wind of doctrine,</hi> there are winds of perſecution that overthrow the houſe upon the ſand, and there are winds of doctrine that toſſe to and fro theſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Scripture mentions chaffe and ſtubble driven
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111056:6"/> with wind, the reed ſhaken with the wind, the wave, the cloud toſſed and carried by the wind. It is becauſe we have no weight in our ſelves, nor ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid principles, that the wind hath power over us; they are light things and moveable, that are at the command of every wind: when the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>wind of doctrine,</hi> he implies that there is no ſolidity; and when he ſaith <hi>every wind,</hi> he implies that there may be contrariety in thoſe doctrins to one another, and yet every one toſſes ſome waves to and fro, and carries ſome cloudes about, nay the very ſame cloud that is now carried one way, is anon carried ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and what a miſerable paſſe is he at, whoſe Religion conſiſts in ſome empty opinion, and is but thereof tenant at curteſie to the next wind that blowes, being carried about with every <note n="g" place="margin">Heinſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> doctrina <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilis.</note> change or novelty of doctrine. There are others that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, not for want of principles and knowledge, but rather want of a good by as of ſincerity for God; being carried about too, but it is by their Intereſts and ends, whereby they are off and on, up and downe as the ſent lies, and as the game which they hunt doth lead them, with theſe I have not much to doe at this time.</p>
            <p>Having thus opened the words of the firſt part, I ſhall now ſum them up together into this point.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Doct.</label> 
               <hi>Children</hi> (that is, ungrounded people who have no ſound bottome of knowledge) <hi>are apt to be toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>Children,</hi> is a word denoting relation or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> relation, and ſo <hi>ye are all the children of God by faith in Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3. 26. Imperfection, ſo in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111056:6"/> that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor. 13. 11. When I was a child I ſpake as a child, &amp;c.</hi> There are many of this deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in the Church, for as in a Schoole there are divers formes, and commonly the moſt Schollers are in the lower, ſo is it in the Church of God, there are abcedaries, babes that are to be taught <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> their letters, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 13, the firſt elements of the oracles of God, and to be fed with the ſpoone, or as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calls it, <hi>milke.</hi> He did not thinke himſelfe too high to feed with <hi>milke, 1 Cor.</hi> 3. 2. Therefore let no Miniſter be he never ſo learned, ſcorne to be an Uſher under Chriſt, to teach his petties their <hi>a. b. c.</hi> If the people had not pleaded their rotten charters of age and marriage againſt Catechiſme, and the Miniſter had not thought himſelfe too good to teach them their letters and firſt elements, we had not ſeen ſo many children carried about with winds of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: Pride (I feare) hath made both aſhamed of the duty, the one to teach, the other to be taught, and I would that both were now humble enough to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the fruit of that neglect.</p>
            <p>Now children are ſo called, by reaſon of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of their knowledge, either in reſpect of the meaſure of it, or of their ungroundedneſſe in it, and its lying looſe in them without rooting.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the meaſure of knowledge, which is low and meane, though themſelves be ſtedfaſt in it and unſhaken: It is not a ſwimming but an ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and centering knowledge, and ſtakes them down from fluctuancy and toſſing, and this is, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſavour, virtue and ſweetneſſe of that they know: He that hath a little knowledge well tryed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111056:7"/> by the touchſtone of the word, and tryed in his own experience to be humbling, quickning and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, he loves the truth, and love will eſtabliſh him in it; upon that reaſon which <hi>Peter</hi> gave to Chriſt, Joh. 6. 68. <hi>Whither ſhould we goe? Thou hast the words of eternall life.</hi> The Apoſtles while under Chriſts owne miniſtery and wing were but very raw in knowledge, (and thereby we learne that no doctrinall teaching or miniſtery, though of Chriſt himſelfe on earth, can make way into the heart of man untill the Spirit come,) yet ſo much they found in the words of Chriſt that they knew not whether elſe to goe, becauſe eternall life was in them; and this teſtimony our people cannot but give to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted Miniſters, that the words of eternall life is in them, and why then will they not reflect upon themſelves and ſay, <hi>whither ſhall we goe?</hi> I would not tread out the leaſt ſparke except it be wildfire in the houſe-eaves which may ſet the whole Towne afire. God hath his babes, to whom I would recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend for their comfort the comparing of <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 13. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 9. where the Apoſtle having called them babes that had need to be taught the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, doth yet ſay, we are perſwaded of you things that accompany ſalvation, and makes mention of their worke and labour of love, for there may be much godlineſſe in leſſer light: Fundamentals unto ſalvation are not ſo many or burdenſome, the leaſt Star in the orbe hath as ſwift and regular a motion though not ſo much light, as the greater; only let it be your endeavour to know your own meaſure,<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 3. 2 Pet. 3. ult.</note> and to encreaſe in grace and in the knowledge of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111056:7"/> Jeſus Chriſt which are practicall things, and not to<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> be queſtion-ſick, and leave wholeſome food to long after ſuch things as doe but adde to the crudity of your ſtomacks, and fill you up with wind.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of their ungroundedneſſe in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which lies looſe in them and doth not ſtake them downe, or anchor them from being toſſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have it by rote, and can neither give a reaſon of that they know, nor have found the weight of it upon judgement and conſcience, and ſo they are variable and unſtable like children; the Philoſophers definition of a <hi>moist element</hi> is proper to them: That<note place="margin">Quod difficulter ſuis, ſacilè alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis terminis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinetur.</note> is (ſaith he) it hath no forme or conſiſtence of its own, but eaſily takes ſuch figure as the continent or veſſell in which it is doth give it, as water takes the forme of the diſh or glaſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into which you put it, ſuch are theſe; they have no mould but what the next teacher caſts them into, being blowne like glaſſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this or that ſhape at the pleaſure of his breath; to ſuch as theſe I commend this, to get the reaſon of that they know, as its ſaid, <hi>a reaſon of the hope that is in you,</hi> for Religion conſiſts not in a rhapſody of looſe opinions, nor will a little knowledge gotten by rote preſerve a man from being taken captive by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very novell doctrine. Its the Apoſtles phraſe, 2 <hi>Tim. 3. 6. They take priſoners ſilly women.</hi> Where you may<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Omnes haereſes ex gynecaei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omat. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtica, <hi>pag. 74.</hi>
               </note> note, that he ſaith they prevaile with women; they get an <hi>Eudoxia, Iuſtina, Conſtantia,</hi> on their ſide, and ſo work upon <hi>Adam</hi> by <hi>Eve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Theſe children are toſſed to and fro, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about, and that denotes;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they are unſtable under the command
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111056:8"/> of every winde, and a prey to every net that is ſpread for them, travelling and wandring through all opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions when they have left the true line; ſometimes they are in <hi>Cancer,</hi> ſometimes in <hi>Capricorne,</hi> falling even into contraries, for one errour is ſtill a bridge to another; ſo we know that the Arminian went forward to Popery, and many of ours from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomianiſme to Anabaptiſme and Browniſme, and whether then? why one errour ingendring with another begets a mule, or mixt off-ſpring, and ſo <hi>Africk</hi> it ſelfe ſhall not ſhow more novelties, <hi>they will encreaſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim. 2. 16.) to more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe.</hi> Errour is a precipice, a <hi>vortex</hi> or whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poole, which firſt turnes men round and then ſucks them in: <hi>be not carried about with divers and ſtrange doctrines,</hi> Heb. 13. 9. <hi>for its good that the heart be</hi> bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt or <hi>stabliſht with grace,</hi> where the oppoſition is evident between being carried about and being eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht by grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they are unprofitably carried; for to what port is the wave toſſed? to what ſtation is the cloud carried? is not the wave bandied back againe by the racket of the next wave, and the cloud by the next wind: Its good (ſaith he) that the heart be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſht, and to that end, that we converſe in ſuch doctrines <hi>as d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e profit them that are exerciſed in them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſtill asking our ſelves this queſtion, what improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is there of my ſoule heavenward by ſuch or ſuch doctrine? what healing of the gaſhes of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? what further inlet or admiſſion into commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt? what cleanſing from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſſe in the feare
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111056:8"/> of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1. If this be your aime, then ſteere this point, intend this ſcope, and let goe queſtions and vaine janglings, contending towards the <hi>end of</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 Tim. 1. 6.</note> 
               <hi>the commandement, which marke</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>many never ſhoot at, 1 Tim.</hi> 1. 6. in their miniſtery or doctrine, nor indeed doe many hearers aime at any ſuch thing, I meane our Nomades (as I may call them) or <hi>walkers,</hi> who will not endure to ſit at the feet of a conſtant godly miniſtery (which yet is the beſt way of proficiency in knowledge and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe) but by reaſon of their feveriſh thirſt, as they diſtaſt each one, ſo they deſire to taſt all waters; of which ſort is he that wanders away the Sabbath by peeping in at Church-dores, and taking eſſay of a ſentence or two, and then, if there be no <hi>ſcratch</hi> for his <hi>itch, lambit &amp; fugit,</hi> he is gone.</p>
            <p>3. Theſe children are toſſed to and fro and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about <hi>by doctrine,</hi> and that implies, that they are hearers that are thus unſetled, and they are teachers by whom they are unſetled.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are hearers, and muſt not they be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers? what elſe, condemned be the atheiſme of the eare of them who turne away their eare from God, who ſpeakes by the hand of his meſſengers; let us leave to the Papiſts <hi>ministorum muta officia, populi caeca obſequia,</hi> the dumbe offices of the Prieſts, and blind obedience of the people, when Scribes and Phariſees hold the chaire, our Saviour ſaith not,<note place="margin">Mark. 4. 24. Luk. 8. 18.</note> heare not, <hi>but take heed how you heare. Take heed what ye heare, beware of their leaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They are teachers that unſettle theſe hearers. They have troubled you with words ſubverting your
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111056:9"/> ſoules, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 24. It much concernes the Church, yea and the State into what hands doctrine is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, by reaſon of the unſettlement of the people which may be occaſioned thereby, I ſhould beſeech them that are in the office of teachers, that they would <hi>take heed to themſelves and to the doctrine, 1 Tim.</hi> 4. 16. and that they would teach milke or meate, and not wind, nor lead on people firſt into criticiſmes, before they have laid in them the plaine Grammar rule of ſound and wholeſome words, that they may be made proſelites to Jeſus Chriſt, not to an opinion; yea though you may beare the name of a party as <hi>Paul</hi> might have done at <hi>Corinth,</hi> yet to cry them downe who would cry you up, and put over your diſciples to Chriſt as <hi>Iohn</hi> did, telling them that ſay I am of <hi>Paul</hi> and I of <hi>Apollo,</hi> that they are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 4.</note> and ſo you will weane them unto Chriſt whoſe they are; As for others that teach indeed but yet are no teachers, (for whatſoever they doe by gifts, yet themſelves are not the gifts of Chriſt unto men in the ſence of the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) I ſhould deſire to know whether every one that hath a gift to be a ſervant muſt therefore be a ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, or that hath gifts enabling him to deliver a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, muſt therefore be an Embaſſadour; If in truth you be as <hi>Amos</hi> ſaid of himſelfe, Herdeſmen or ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of Sycomore fruit, then you muſt produce<note place="margin">Amos 7. 14, 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> your extraordinary commiſſion as he did, ſaying, <hi>And the Lord took me as I followed the flock and ſaid, goe propheſie to my people Iſrael,</hi> or elſe you muſt be taken to be but Herdſmen ſtill, and ſo it will be no wonder that ſtrange teachers ſhould carry credulous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111056:9"/> people about with <hi>ſtrange doctrines,</hi> as the Apoſtle cals them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 9.</p>
            <p>4. The doctrine by which theſe children are toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to and fro, and carried about, is called <hi>wind,</hi> and that doth not denote the pure Word of God, but ſome illegitimate doctrine which the adulterers and raviſhers of the truth doe beget upon it: what here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ever came abroad without <hi>verbum Domini</hi> in the mouth of it. The Arrian pleaded out of that text <hi>Iohn 14. 28. The Father is greater than I.</hi> The Anabaptiſt from that, <hi>Matth. 28. 19. Goe ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and diſciple all nations,</hi> and when he ſhall be thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or full ſtature he will undermine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy by that <hi>Rom. 12. 19. Avenge not your ſelves.</hi> The Antinomian hath for his plea that 1 <hi>Tim. 1. 9. The law is not made for a righteous man,</hi> arguing that he who hath Evangelicall grace for his principle of obedience ſhould not have the law for a rule thereof; as if a new principle and an old rule might not ſtand together: but becauſe I intend not a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of theſe or the like errours, therefore finally, you all know that the devill hath a <hi>ſcriptum eſt</hi> ready <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 6. the Spider ſucks poyſon out of the Roſe, not that I would imply that there is any ſuch thing in the Word it ſelfe (for <hi>ex veris nil niſi verum</hi>) but that a corrupt ſtomacke concocts wholeſome food into diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>And why <hi>wind of doctrine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe there is no ſolidity in it, but being wind it breeds but wind in the hearer and not good bloud; and here I cannot but bewaile our Pulpits of late times, filled with hay and ſtubble in ſtead of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111056:10"/> gold and ſilver, as namely, invectives againſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Cavaliers, newes, and novell opinions, and in the mean time the ſtaple commodities of Heaven, as Chriſt, Faith, Love, &amp;c. are laid aſide like breath'd ware which no body cals for; I would not be thought to be a patron of any ſuch obnoxious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt whom the Word of God ſhoots an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is I plead for, that people who come to looke for ſoul-nouriſhing food may not be ſerved with ſcumme and froth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe of the changeableneſſe, variety and novelty of it; for indeed ſuch teachers doe fit their lettice to the lips of their auditory and doe eaſily take them by their itching eares; nothing more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to an Athenian eare than novelty, which affects the hearers while it is freſh and green, but when they ſhall come to chew this wind, they find nothing in it, and ſo they hunt about againe untill they ſtart a new notion. Chriſt is the onely everlaſting meat, who though he be like a great ſtanding <hi>diſh,</hi> which by reaſon of Kickſhawes and fine Sallets is now adayes not much fed upon by many; yet a truly humble ſoule is never weary of Chriſt, neither can ſit downe to a meale, I meane, heare a Sermon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, and this ſound appetite is a ſigne of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent temperament and healthfull conſtitution of ſpirit; he that hath his mouth in taſt for ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and his ſtomacke craving ſuch ſolid food, hath cauſe to bleſſe God, who it may be by inward ſhakings and temptations cals him to the ſetling of the main free-holt, and ſtate of his ſoule, and ſo takes him off from running himſelfe out of breath after
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111056:10"/> novelties and niceties, which will ſooner fill his head with dreames than his heart with ſtrength or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe of its prevalencie with and over un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayed men, one would wonder that this which the Apoſtle cals wind of doctrine ſhould ſo prevaile and ſpread; how ſuddenly is a whole countrey leaven'd with it? whereas the ſaving knowledge and recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt, the power of godlineſſe, and ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall may be preacht an age, and not ſo many fiſh be taken as are taken at one draught by a corrupt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; I will not borrow that compariſon which <hi>Euſebius</hi> made choice of to expreſſe the quick ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of the Goſpell at the firſt, ſaying, that it paſſed through the world like a Sun-beame; but I ſhall take that of the Apoſtle 2 <hi>Tim. 2. 17. Their word ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth like a gangrene,</hi> which preſently overruns the parts and takes the brain, as this wind of doctrine doth, and the ſame Apoſtle (than whom no man did more counter-worke falſe teachers) ſaith, <hi>Acts 20. 30. they ſhall ſpeake perverſe things, to draw diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples after them,</hi> whereby it ſeemes that the way to draw diſciples is to ſpeake perverſe things; hereunto agreeing is that of our Saviour, <hi>Ioh. 5. 43. I am come in my Fathers Name, and ye receive me not: If another ſhall come in his owne name, him will ye receive.</hi> Chriſt cannot finde entertainment but <hi>Bacchochebas</hi> is followed, and the reaſon is, becauſe Truth when it commeth hath nothing in us, but errour hath: There is no tinder to catch a ſparke of truth, but there is oyle for the wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire of errour. Hereſies are workes of the fleſh,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111056:11"/> 
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 19, 20. therefore men are <hi>ſoone removed, Gal.</hi> 1. 6. from truth to errour.</p>
            <p>And now to draw up this point into a ſumme, by way of Application:</p>
            <p>1. Conſider the doctrine you heare, and tell it over againe from the hand of the teacher, a man will tell money after his father. <hi>Beware lest any man make prize of you, Col.</hi> 2. 8. ſome there are to whom the reputation and worth of the teacher is the proofe of his doctrine, receiving all that is ſtamped with his <hi>ipſe dixit. We ſhould not call any man our father on earth, Matth.</hi> 23. 9. and ſome alſo thinke it enough to ſay, <hi>This doctrine makes moſt against ſuperſtition and popery,</hi> and yet we will not abide that in a <hi>Maldonat,</hi> who ſhall rather pitch upon ſuch a ſenſe of Scripture, becauſe it makes moſt againſt the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> and there are who falling upon ſome novell opinion doe honeſtate it with the name of a <hi>new light,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves the greateſt illuminates, as having two eyes and all the world beſides but one, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it not, but that every man in his Regeneration hath a new light, which is a part of the new creature, for the new creation begins in a <hi>fiat lux;</hi> Nor doe I deny but that in the Church there may be a clearer and further demonſtration of and inſight into many things in the Scriptures, which have lien in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the pit, and may be brought neerer day than aforetime, for the neerer to the end the more glory and light, as its ſaid <hi>Dan. 12. 4. Shut up the words, and ſeale the book, even to the time of the end: many ſhall run to and fro, and knowledge ſhall be increaſed.</hi> But this light though new to us, yet it is not new to the word,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111056:11"/> to the Sun light is not new, though it be to the Moon, as the Apoſtle cals <hi>ſtrange doctrines, Heb.</hi> 13. 9. not ſuch as are new to us, but ſuch as are forreine to the word: ſo we call that ſtrange light, rather then new, which the word of God ownes not, as the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring thereof, and therefore I exhort you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether this light come from the Word, or rather doe not ſhine from a glo-worme in your own fancies? Is not this viſion of yours <hi>extra mittendo,</hi> by beames going out of your owne eyes to the object<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doe you not firſt conceive, and then goe forth to ſeek a father for your child? as the Sadduces that firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the Reſurrection, and then think that they can make their hereſie good, out of a caſe in <hi>Moſes</hi> law, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether it doe nouriſh thoſe graces in you in which the Kingdome of God conſiſts? or whether doth not this new light ſtarve you? doth not this ſun-ſhine put out your fire? for whether it be that the intention of the minde upon the vaine theory of opinions doth divert the ſtreame, and leaves (as I may ſay) practicke godlineſſe dry; or whether God withdraw his influences from them that lay them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out in toyes? or whatſoever the cauſe be, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſheweth that after this <hi>vertigo</hi> takes men in the head, many of them decay in the vitals of Religion, and turne either Polititians to erect a party, or grow very leane in practicke godlineſſe, and draw looſe in their geeres, if indeed they become not looſe in their lives and wayes.</p>
            <p>2. This point may give us juſt occaſion to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111056:12"/> into the reaſon why we are ſo toſſed to and fro and carried about, and crumbled into diviſions, for who is a ſtranger in Iſrael that he ſhould not know theſe things. The heavens are filled with fixed ſtars without number, but the Planets are no more than ſeven; if the proportion was caſt up amongſt us our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>), as <hi>Iude</hi> cals them <hi>ver.</hi> 13. doe hold a greater proportion to our fixed ſtarres. Is not our Church called to the barre to anſwer not ſo much for her purity or chaſtitie in all Adminiſtrations as for her very being and life? what children are theſe, that will unmother her, before God her husband have divorced and unwifed her? that will throw Babylon in her face, and then juſtifie their ſeceſſion and departure by <hi>Flee out of Babylon:</hi> which will not ſerve their turne except they can find alſo a <hi>Goe out of Epheſus, out of Pergamus, out of Sardis, out of Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Our Sacraments are alſo called to the barre. The Lords Supper, under the reaſon of a <hi>mixt Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> by which (as I conceive) is not meant that unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers or unregenerate perſons doe partake <hi>rem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenti</hi> the kernell of this ordinance; for in that reſpect they have no Communion with the faithfull: but that the Company of Communicants in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſeale is mixt of regenerate and unregenerate, Saints and hypocrites; unto which we ſay, that though the doore ought to be more narrow than to let in <hi>dogs and ſwine,</hi> yet the preſence and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of intruders doth not evacuate that Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the faithfull have with Chriſt, and among themſelves: for the Maſter of the great Feaſt (as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111056:12"/> He obſerved,) <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 12. doth not ſay to them that had the wedding garment; how came you in hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſuch a man, but <hi>Friend, how camest thou in hither not having a wedding garment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Baptiſme is ſaid to be a vanity, a nullity, as being diſpenſed to infants, and that becauſe we want example for it: but ſo we doe, for womens recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lords Supper: and if the reaſon and equity of the rule will carry it for women as well as men, then alſo we ſhall joyne iſſue in that point, and make it good upon that ground, for children of beleeving parents as for the parents themſelves: for are not ſuch<note place="margin">See a learned Treatiſe called <hi>The Birth pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge.</hi>
               </note> infants <hi>foederati,</hi> confederates and in the Covenant, though they cannot actually reſtipulate, yea ſurely, as well as thoſe which were circumciſed.</p>
            <p>The morall Law is queſtioned, whether it be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to and directory of a beleever in Chriſt; for becauſe he hath another bridle of reſtraint of him from ſin, and another ſpurre incentive of him unto obedience, therefore he hath not the ſame rule: which is but a confounding of the principle where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and of the rule according to which a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is acted; theſe men are much miſtaken in that place whereupon they ſeeme to ground their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Rom. 7. 6. <hi>That we ſhould ſerve in newneſse of ſpirit, and not in the oldneſſe of the letter.</hi> Where they oppoſe theſe two as a rule and principle, taking away the rule, called (ſay they) the oldneſſe of the letter, by the principle which is the newneſſe of the Spirit; now there is nothing more cleere, then that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, oppoſes not the rule, to the principle of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; but <hi>duo principia,</hi> or rather <hi>duos ſerviendi
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111056:13"/> modos,</hi> two manners of ſerving, in the one of which they were bond-men, in the other free-men.</p>
            <p>Our Miniſtery is arraigned alſo, as the Papiſts, becauſe the Miniſters of many Reformed Churches have not Impoſition of the hands of a Biſhop, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny their ordination to be legitimate, ſo is ours de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, becauſe we had; We are between two mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, what Miniſters will they find in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt for many hundred yeares if this be good againſt ordination? I cannot conceive but God owned ſome of them for his witneſſes prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying in ſackcloth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 3.</p>
            <p>And finally to the nullity of theſe; the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Sacraments, the Morall Law, the Miniſtery, is added, the <hi>Mortality of the ſoule,</hi> which if reaſon cannot confute, let a man conſult conſcience, if that cannot, Scripture will; had it not been a ſtrange mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake in our bleſſed Saviour to have (but in a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) ſuppoſed a rich man after his death in torment and <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome; if the ſoule be not immortall, or at leaſt if it ſurvive not; for that cannot be applied to the reſurrection, when the rich man will have no brethren on earth to ſend unto, neither can there be any ſence in that portion of Scripture, but upon ſuppoſall of the ſoule outliving the body.</p>
            <p>I had rather draw a curtaine before this face of things then paint it out unto you. How ſad a hearing is it to heare I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> I am of <hi>Apollo,</hi> I am of <hi>Cephas:</hi> was not this that which (as <hi>Ierome</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) did at firſt ſet up Biſhops: our diviſions are their factours, but that is not all; more ſad it is to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111056:13"/> heare, <hi>here is Chriſt, and there is Chriſt,</hi> for we are ſo impotent in our opinions, that every man makes his own to be the very Shibboleth of the Church; a thing unheard of before our times, that men of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Trades in this famous City, can be all of one Company, but being of divers opinions they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be of one Church, nor will be all of one Schoole except they be all of one forme, which breakes our communion into fragments; Now what may be the cauſe of this tranſportation of people, are they chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ungrounded in knowledge? that is too much to be feared, or are they proud and wanton, and have taken ſurfet of the great things of the Law? or are they aſhamed to ſtand in the levell of ſober pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall Chriſtians, but muſt be maſters and ſet up the trade of ſome new opinion for themſelves, and build <hi>Babel</hi> to get a name, and to be ſome body in in the eyes of a party? I know not what to ſay, but the Lord ſtop the gangrene, and turne all our eyes to the great things of the Law, that ſo this tithing of mint and cummin may be left to a ſecond place.</p>
            <p>3. Be not children, and oh that this word might ſtop the fury of your precipitate levity, as <hi>Coeſar</hi> did the ſedition of his Army by one word, <hi>Quirites;</hi> you have had the vitals of Religion, a holy and pure doctrine, and there is not another Goſpell. For Miniſters that have burn'd and ſhined them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out in holding forth eſſentials and ſaving truths, the whole world ſince the Apoſtles time could not overmatch you; and for Chriſtians (the ſeale of their Miniſtery) begotten and bred up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſhadow, in reſpect of the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111056:14"/> there hath not been another <hi>England</hi> on earth, ſince that time; I doe not aſcribe this to the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and diſcipline (no more then I doe aſcribe the multiplying of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) but under God to the paines and diligence of faithfull paſtours, whom I would not have any man now to undervalue and debaſe as brats of Antichriſt: they were <hi>Heroes</hi> and Worthies, our regeneration and faith are their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, let no man digge up their aſhes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade them in eſteeme, nor belch out poiſon againſt the learning, livings, callings of their godly ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in this Church; for wiſe men will interpret that they doe it upon no other reaſon then <hi>Herod</hi> burnt the Regiſtries of the families and genealogies of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in conſciouſneſſe of his own obſcurity; And as for this Church, certainely ſhe hath had a wombe to beare children, and breaſts to give them ſuck, which two things doe make a faire proofe for her againſt all calumnies, though alas ſhe had alſo a generarion of vipers eating through her bowels. Finally, This Kingdome owes as much to Religion as any in the world, we have ſeene wonders of Gods love and miracles of deliverance, and if God ſhall now bring his Arke to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and ſet it up in greater ſtate then before time, let us dance before it, but withall let us not deſpiſe the houſe of <hi>Obed-Edom</hi> which God bleſſed for the Arke ſake; we muſt not put downe the Temple becauſe its made a den of theeves, but rather whip them out of it: and for that we faſt and pray, as alſo that thoſe ſeven <hi>Ones</hi> in the fourth and fifth verſes may continue with us for ever, <hi>One body, and one ſpirit, one hope of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111056:14"/> your calling, one Lord, one Faith, one baptiſme, one God and Father of all,</hi> which ſhould be as ſo many quoines to lock together all parts of the building in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one, as indeed they would if men were not ſo opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion-big as to make every extravagant or at leaſt extrinſicall opinion fundamentall, and as an <hi>Atlas</hi> to a new-Church building.</p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond part of the Text, which is the haracter or deſcription of the impoſtours and ſeducers, that doe unſettle men, whereof I ſhall open the termes or words.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Sleight of men.</hi> The originall word for ſleight, doth properly ſignifie Dice-playing, and by ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor taken from players at Dice (which ſort of men you ſhall ſeldome reade of in ſober authours without ſome brand of infamie,) it ſets out the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of falſe teachers, and in this all agree, but then in the very point of application of this ſimilitude there is a little difference.</p>
            <p>1. As the caſt of the Die is changeable and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>alea nihil incertius,</hi> ſo are theſe teachers and ſuch is their doctrine, and therefore he calls it <hi>ſleight of men,</hi> oppoſing this doctrine of theirs to that of Gods pure word, which is alwayes like it ſelfe and hath no intereſts, paſſions, crooked ends, as men have.</p>
            <p>2. As dice-players can cogge the Die and make it anſwer what caſt they pleaſe, ſo theſe teachers, have an act of mixing and adulterating the word, ſo as to make it anſwer their own profit or advantage, but whether it be ſo or ſo, or both wayes, you ſee what theſe teachers make of their hearers, meere table<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111056:15"/> which the dice-player carries hither and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and moves from point to point as he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Cunning craftineſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The ſame word that is uſed to expreſſe the ſubtilty of the ſerpent tempting<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Eve,</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 3. <hi>He beguiled</hi> Eve <hi>through his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty,</hi> and it ſignifies the deep policie of men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 19. He taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſſe, and ſo it imports that theſe teachers are veterators, beaten fellowes, men exerciſed and skilfull to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>They lye in wait to deceive,</hi> And the word in this Text is alſo uſed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 11. that ye may be able<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (ſaith he) to ſtand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; againſt the ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems of the Devill; for it ſignifies properly an ambuſhment or ſtratagem of warre, whereby the enemy ſets upon a man <hi>ex inſidijs,</hi> at unawares, deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſpecious and faire overtures and pretences of falſe teachers, ſpreading their net under the chaffe, to catch the ſilly bird, for it is plaine that all their ſleight and craftineſſe is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to this very end and purpoſe, that they may entrap and catch men within the ambuſh of their impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures.</p>
            <p>That which I collect from this part of the Text, is,</p>
            <p>
               <label>Doct. 1.</label> What oddes the Apoſtle makes between the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer and the ſeduced, even as much as between an old fowler and a young bird, the one he calls <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> ſimple, eaſie, credulous people, the the other is a ſhrewd gameſter, a man of ſubtilty and ſtratagems. I cannot therefore but upon this obſervation, exhort you to take heed of playing with ſuch, ſtake down nothing, eſpecially not your ſoules, come not within
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111056:15"/> their ambuſh. I wonder that petties and novices in knowledge will forſake the Congregations and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen aſſemblies of Gods people, to frequent private houſes where theſe teachers lay their ambuſcado; would not all men condemne the folly of a young man of a great eſtate, that ſhould deale with a crafty gameſter? for theſe ſeducers whoſe deſigne is to make merchandiſe of their hearers, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 3. doe moſt of all aime at them who are good prize, they care not much for a ſheep that hath not a good fleece. I beſeech you be wiſe, you may be caught, though you meane it not, God may give you up captive to error for your vanity in forſaking his aſſemblies: Haply you reſolve that you will not be caught; no more did <hi>Dinah</hi> intend to be defiled when ſhe went forth to ſee the daughters of the Land, or <hi>Peter</hi> to deny Chriſt when he went to the high Prieſts hall; there is no man but will beleeve a lye when God gives him up to deluſion, one may be infected with the plague by looking in at the window, our nature is apt to receive impreſſions of error. Its obſerved of ſheep, that they eate no graſſe more greedily then that which rots them, <hi>wherefore if they ſhall ſay unto you behold he is in the deſart, goe not forth, behold he is. in the ſecret chambers, beleeve it not, Matth.</hi> 24. 26. And what may ſome ſay, would you have us come up to an Idols Temple and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate in Idolatry? No, <hi>Come not ye to</hi> Gilgal, <hi>nor goe up to</hi> Bethaven, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. 15. Woods and caves, and the Ile of <hi>Pathmos</hi> are to be preferred to ſuch aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; or ſhould Chriſtians abſtaine all private mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and confine their Religion as many doe to a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111056:16"/> Church and a common-Prayer booke? farre be it from us: Antichriſt and Popery will feele the wounds of ſuch private Aſſemblies as long as they draw any breath, the enemies of God and his Church know what reaſon they have to hate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles (as they call them:) All that I have to ſay is, that you ſtick faſt unto and make uſe of your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and teachers, which are the gifts of Jeſus Chriſt unto his Church, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. and that you come not into the ſecret of theſe who are deſcribed <hi>ver.</hi> 14. by their ſleight and ſubtilty to deceive.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Doct. 2.</label> Seducers are artiſts and crafteſ-maſters in ſleight and ſubtilty, and ſtratagems of deceit, they have ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices, and wayes, and methods to take men at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, and to convey their poiſon privily; <hi>who pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 1. they will not reſiſt the truth <hi>aperto marte,</hi> but cunningly undermine it, <hi>as</hi> Jannes <hi>and</hi> Jambres <hi>withſtood</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſo doe theſe alſo reſiſt the truth,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 8. that is by ſleight and counterfeiting to doe the ſame thing, ſo that one ſhall have much adoe to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſerpents of <hi>Moſes</hi> and them of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, <hi>for they alſo did the like by their inchantments, Exod.</hi> 7. 11. It ſeemes theſe ſeducers are men of parts, the Apoſtle deſcribes them in the ſame words as the old ſerpent is deſcribed, by whoſe ſubtilty we exchanged Paradiſe for thiſtles and bryers; which firſt example ſhould teach us for ever to take heed of them, that are of his breede, <hi>who was more ſubtill then any beaſt of the field;</hi> that which being ſanctified or well imployed, might be called wiſedome, being corrupted and abuſed is called craftineſſe, therefore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111056:16"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, though uſually taken in the worſer part, for<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Druſius</hi> in Job cap. 5. ver. 13.</note> ſubtilty and cunning, yet ſometimes it ſignifies wiſedome and lawfull policie, there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a good and honeſt craftineſſe or policie, whereby a Miniſter being a fiſher of men, may catch ſuch as by indiſcretion will otherwiſe be hardned, ſcandalized and loſt both to himſelfe and God; we are in great want of this policie of diſcretion in the management of our Miniſtery, by breaking old bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles with new wine, and by expoſing Religion to contempt of them whom we might have either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced or at leaſt diſarmed of occaſion againſt the truth; but no farther upon this point: I muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that I am upon the ſubtilty and ſtratagems of impoſtours that lie in wait to ſeduce, ſome of which I ſhall point out unto you, as I find them in the Scriptures, that ſo you may performe that duty which is more than once enjoyned upon you in this caſe, that is <hi>beware.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The common deſigne of all falſe teachers, is to <hi>make merchandiſe</hi> of people, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 3. they negotiate their own ends, and have an eye to the ſtake when they caſt the die, their credit, profit, luſts are the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to which they draw every line, <hi>they have eyes full of adultery, and their heart is exerciſed in covetouſneſſe, they follow the way of</hi> Balaam <hi>who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſſe, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 14, 15. and the Apoſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeches the brethren to <hi>marke ſuch which cauſe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and offences, becauſe they that are ſuch ſerve not our Lord Ieſus Chriſt but their own belly,</hi> Rom. 16. 18. but how doth the Apoſtle know this? for mens ends lie cloſe; and how is it that he ſeemes to charge it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111056:17"/> upon all of them? Are they all covetous? have all of them eyes full of adultery? doe they all make their belly their God, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Its true, that ends lie cloſe, a man may deny one and ſeeke another, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> laies by his great repute gotten by ſorcery, to ſeeke himſelfe in getting power by laying on of hands to give the holy Ghoſt, and this he carried ſo cunningly as to paſſe with <hi>Philip</hi> undiſcovered pride may be trampled upon in pride, and books written againſt vaine-glory only to get glory, bye ends may be preacht againſt, even out of bye ends; as all that bowle at the ſame marke doe not take the ſame ground, ſo men in ſeeking themſelves, may drive ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall trades; one is for credit, another for his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat, another for his purſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but this in the generall will hold good, <hi>ſeducers are ſelf ſeekers.</hi> For the ſervice of this maine deſigne theſe and ſuch like are their arts or method.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Apoſtle tells us, that <hi>by good words and faire ſpeeches they deceive the hearts of the ſimple,</hi> Rom. 16. 18. the word he uſeth for ſimple, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men that are otherwiſe not evill, or as we vulgarly call them, harmeleſſe, innocent men, eaſie to be led aſide; It ſhould ſeeme the Corinthian teachers, with whom <hi>Paul</hi> had ſuch bickerings, had a faculty of pithanology or perſwaſive lenociny of words, whereby they did <hi>ſuadendo docere,</hi> not ſo much convince by evidence of truth as perſwade with woing words; It concernes very much <hi>to hold faſt the forme of wholeſome words,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 13. which the Apoſtle oppoſeth to <hi>questions and logomachies or strife of words and perverſe diſputings,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 3, 4, 5.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111056:17"/> 
               <hi>as alſo to prophane and vaine bablings,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 16.<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illa duo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; novi mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di. <hi>Chem. loc. com.</hi>
               </note> and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 20. that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or as ſome reade <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, empty words, and novell expreſſions: you all know that by loſing the genuine and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per meaning of the word Church and Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we had almoſt forgot the Scripture uſe of them, and brought the Church within the pale of the Clergy, and the Biſhop into a throne above the Miniſters of the word; The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, hath an expreſſion or two to this purpoſe, <hi>They ſpeake great ſwelling words of vanity,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 18. that is, they ſpeake great bubbles of words full of wind, ſtrong lines, or bigge fancies to beare downe people by that torrent; and againe in the 2 <hi>Pet. 2. 3. through covetouſneſſe ſhall they with fained words make</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>merchandiſe of you.</hi> What are theſe fained words? doe not they meane the ſame as that 1 <hi>Tim. 4. 2. ſpeaking lies in hypocriſie,</hi> or ſhould it not rather be taken for a ſet and compoſed forme of words, ſuch as Merchants uſe in commending their wares to ſale; ſhewing the goodneſſe and properties of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity they deſire to put off, and even belying it into credit, for to that the words ſeeme to allude: I ſhall not dwell upon this, but certainely it is not for nothing that ſeducers are found to hide their hooke under words and expreſſions, which they doe arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially fit and compoſe for the purpoſe; a good Title ſells a ſorry Booke; And all times will beare witneſſe that it hath been the property of ſuch men as have had any monſter to bring to light, to uſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and cloudineſſe of expreſſion, that what is unſhapen and without forme at the firſt may after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111056:18"/> be lickt into proportion; errors are baſhfull at firſt, and comming out of the darke cannot looke broad-waken upon the light, and therefore they are by their parents or nurſes alwayes ſwathed up in clouts of ambiguity, as the Oracles of old lapt up their <hi>Effata,</hi> or as he that wrote <hi>Edvardum regem occidere nolite timere bonum est,</hi> where the comma helps him out at which doore he pleaſes; thus the <hi>ſepia</hi> goes away in her own inke, and the doore is left halfe chare to make eſcape.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They baite their hooke with ſuch baites as are proper to the fiſh thy would catch: Els they were not good anglers, to which the Apoſtle ſeemes to compare them, in that word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 18. which is to allure as a bait doth the fiſh. And what is that bait? ſee ver. 19. <hi>they promiſe them liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> there is not a more catching bait then <hi>liberty;</hi> Is it likely that Jeſus Chriſt or his Miniſters that preach a yoke, a daily croſſe, a forſaking all for him, ſhould make ſuch great draughts of fiſh, as they that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe liberty?</hi> but what liberty, haply they may call it Chriſtian liberty, or liberty of conſcience, ſo the ſerpent ſaid, <hi>ye ſhall be as gods,</hi> but what is it indeed; Is it not a liberty from the controll or check of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours and their authority, for <hi>they deſpiſe dominion</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 2. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and ſpeake evill of dignities,</hi> Jude 8. and therefore doth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much call for obedience and ſubjection to Magiſtrates, Maſters, Miniſters, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by anticipating or correcting the thoughts of Libertiniſme, unto which the name of <hi>Goſpell liberty</hi> might be abuſed: ſurely our Lord Chriſt hath not brought in a <hi>ſaturnalia</hi> or exemption of Chriſtians
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111056:18"/> from the Scepter of Government, or the rod of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline. Nor is liberty of Conſcience (though ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and inviolable) a freedome to be or doe what we will: for by that engine the ſword might be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiped out of the Magiſtrates, and the Keyes out of the Churches hand; and then we ſhould find our ſelves returned to a Chaos without forme and void; I doe not wonder that all ſorts of ſects and hereſies (though they be of contrary principles in particular) ſhould meet and concurre in this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to live by their owne lawes, unaccountable to others, and independent; Thoſe that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Independents are farre off from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Church to be ſuch a <hi>Romulus</hi> his <hi>aſylum,</hi> a Sanctuary for all commers; they allow that Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem ſhall reach forth her hand as farre as Antioch; neither (I thinke) doe they plead the letting alone of the tares untill the harveſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 30. againſt the cenſures of the Church or the <hi>faſces &amp; ſecurim</hi> of the Magiſtrate; but I am ſure of this, that he that ſaith, <hi>Let both grow together untill the harveſt,</hi> doth not give way to any man to ſow them. <hi>An enemy hath done this:</hi> but enough of this at this time. There are others that goe about with liberty too, and cry, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from the obligation of the Morall Law as a rule; a liberty from poenitentiall ſorrowes, faſtings, humiliations to them that are regenerate; a liberty from ſinning, or if not ſo, yet from asking pardon for it, if they be in Chriſt. Theſe are great liberties indeed, but they are glorious liberties, reſerved unto another world, if any man promiſe you them here on earth, he takes upon him to antedate the time of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111056:19"/> them. There are certain fruits and effects of Chriſts Redemption of us, which are payable only in the world to come; There is yet another liberty which ſome will promiſe, and that is a liberty of ſenſuall luſts, and fleſhly looſneſſe. It was <hi>Balaams</hi> bait whereby he invited the Iſraelites to the idolatry of <hi>Baal-Peor,</hi> and the Apoſtle findes theſe falſe teachers baiting their hooke with the ſame 2 <hi>Pet. 2. 18. they allure through the luſts of the fleſh, through much wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe:</hi> and <hi>ver. 14. Having eyes full of adulteries, or of an adultereſſe,</hi> as the originall carries it; and again, <hi>ver. 2. many ſhall follow their laſcivious wayes:</hi> for ſome copies have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But you will ſay, Is there any ſuch affinity betweene ſeducing by doctrine and ſenſuality? How is it that the Apoſtle charges theſe teachers with ſuch filthy luſts? I ſhall anſwer but little to this queſtion, as God for idolatry, which is ſpirituall fornication, gives men and women up to that which is corporall: for its ſaid <hi>Rom. 1. 25, 26. They changed the truth of God into a lie: for this cauſe God gave them up to vile affections,</hi> ſo will God ſhame and diſcredit the errours that are ſet up againſt his truth by the luſts that keep company with them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> They undervalue and caſt dirt in the face of all that ſtand in their light, this is an old way of inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating into people, the wolves perſwade the ſheepe that their Shepherds feed them, to fleece them, that ſo they may the eaſilyer worry them; It is not much that we are called legall Preachers, time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers, perſecutours, inquiſitours, what not? The devill muſt firſt aſperſe God to <hi>Eve</hi> before he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with her, and thoſe popular preachers could
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111056:19"/> not reigne at Corinth but by bringing <hi>Paul</hi> into diſ-eſteeme, if they could; <hi>His letters, ſay they, are weighty and powerfull, but his bodily preſence is weake, and his ſpeech contemptible, 2 Cor.</hi> 10. 10. Its eaſie for men to ingratiate themſelves with their party by eſpying faults in every Ordinance and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion never ſo well conſtituted; we ſee beauty enough and find no want of light in the Sun, though they that look upon it through their Galilean glaſſes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſpots in it as big as all Aſia or Africk, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> They wreſt the Scriptures, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 16. making it to ſpeake upon the rack<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that which it never meant; partiality and affection to their own opinion is an ill <hi>medium</hi> to look through: Pull the ſtaffe out of the water, and it will not be crooked; how often doe men <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> compell the Scriptures to goe two mile, when of themſelves they will goe but one, we ſhould tremble to put words into the mouth of thoſe Oracles, which we doe by miſ-inferences, and miſapplications. 1. By miſ-inference drawing forth that which they will not yeeld, as the Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces proved no Reſurrection, becauſe ſeven brethren had taken one woman to wife, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 28. unto whom our Saviour anſwers, that though they cited a place of Scripture, yet they erred not knowing the Scripture; for not he that repeats the words, but takes up the true ſence, is the man that knowes the Scriptures. We muſt not mangle and cut one joynt from another, and expound one ſentence againſt the whole ſtreame. I would men would tremble to take Gods hand which he hath ſet to his owne
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111056:20"/> Word, and ſet it to a lie of their owne: it were odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to ſerve a man ſo. 2. By miſ-application of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rules to particulars. For it hath been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that it is a great cauſe of many evils not to be able to adapt common principles and generall rules to particular caſes or actions; for how often is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule of Scripture brought for the warrant of an unlawfull action? as if the Apoſtle ſhould have eaten with ſcandall, upon the rule of <hi>All things are pure to the pure;</hi> ſo we know, how men firſt imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a decency and order in ſuperſtitious ceremonies, and then warranted them by that, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order;</hi> we feare not to ſay, that no man can prove the calling of our Miniſters, or the Baptiſme of our infants, or the Morall Law to be null, &amp;c. but by the torture of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> They recommend their doctrine upon ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate pretended revelation and light of their owne, or by ſome effects thereof which they ſeeme to have found in themſelves ſince they became therewith acquainted; as that they have found ſuch experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it in themſelves as they never had before, they are more lively, cheerefull, comfortable, &amp;c. As for their revelations or light, what is it they meane by them? Doe they meane that the vaile is taken off the Scripture or rather their eye, ſo that they have a cleerer ſpirituall diſcerning into, and ſavour of, and affection to the Word? or doe they meane by revelation, ſome ſecret ſealings or aſſurances which are indeed private to their owne ſoules, like the white ſtone of abſolution with their owne names written thereon. Theſe are admirable firſt-fruits of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111056:20"/> the Spirit and of glory; Happy are they to whom God in this wilderneſſe gives to taſte theſe Cluſters of Canaan-Grapes; And for the effects of the word which they find in themſelves, as atteſtations of the truth, power, and goodneſſe of the word. I find the Apoſtle appealing to the ſenſe of beleevers, to atteſt the doctrine of the Goſpel, <hi>Gal. 3. 2. received ye the Spirit by the preaching of the law, or by the hearing of faith?</hi> but now what is all this to the revelation or effects of <hi>new and ſtrange doctrines?</hi> what impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures have not been obtruded upon pretence of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate light and revelation, the old Prophet may bring you into the lions mouth by telling you of an angel that ſpoke to him, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 13. 18. &amp; 24. God ſaith that he <hi>proves his people by a Prophet, or dreamer of dreames, to know whether they love the Lord their God, with all their heart, and with all their ſoule, Deut.</hi> 13. 3. nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, nor Apoſtle, nor Angel is to be heard if he preach <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> beſides or other than that ye have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 8.</note> and for that they ſay that they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as it were in a new world ſince they found this new way. I much queſtion their <hi>probatum eſt,</hi> Is it not ſome angel of darkneſſe transformed into an Angel of light? doe they not walke in the light of their fire, and the ſparkes that they have kindled, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 50. 11. It muſt needs be an eaſie way; when a man hath caſt off all trouble for ſin and all care of holy duties: but ſurely the way is too broad to be good. Theſe principles, <hi>I ought not to ſorrow for ſin, leaſt I diſparage the ſufficiencie of Chriſts ſatisfaction: I can pay no obedience to the law, but I muſt thereby either infringe my Chriſtian liberty, or joyne merit with Chriſt;</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:111056:21"/> muſt needs worke a ſtrange alteration, becauſe the doctrine is ſtrange.</p>
            <p>I would ſpeake a word from this point to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and to the people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the Miniſters, you ſee theſe impoſtours have ſleight and ſubtilty to lie in wait for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and whom doth it concerne but you to take heed to the flock, you cannot by ſilence <hi>liberare ſidem aut animam;</hi> Chriſt hath given Paſtours and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to his Church to this end, that the people ſhould not be children, toſſed to and fro, &amp;c. convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of gain-ſayers, and ſtopping the mouthes of ſoul-ſubverting teachers doth belong to your office, <hi>Titus</hi> 1. 9, 10, 11. if there were but one Heterodox teacher ſtart up, and neglected by the people, you would diſcharge at him, with as much freedome as at Papiſts; what if there be moe ſuch teachers and followed by thouſands, is it ever the more truth for the number? or is it a <hi>noli me tangere?</hi> or are we ſlaves to popularity? and dare not ſnatch the ſouls of our people out of the ſtreame for feare of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing them by ſaving of them? or have we no hope to worke a cure, and ſo like Phiſitians, we let deſperate patients eat and drinke, and doe what they will without contradiction? <hi>Luther</hi> did not much conſider how uſefull the Sectaries of his time might have been againſt the Pope and his party, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed them freely, knowing that they more blemiſht and hindred the Reformation by their tenets, than were likely to help it with their hands; I would not blow the trumpet or proclaime open warre againſt leſſer differences, ſeverity and acrimony in ſuch
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111056:21"/> caſes breedes ſchiſme and heales it not; but perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious errours and deſtructive to ſoules (which it is cruelty to ſpare and not pity) muſt be faced and fought againſt, not with invectives and railing, that doth but anger the Gangrene, and is not the way to quench wildfire, but by ſolid convictions and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of truth: for ſo you ſhall either gain a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or not loſe a friend. But you may aske, when ſhould we goe out againſt a doctrine as pernicious; for even that point about the law which denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates an <hi>Antinomian,</hi> and that about Baptiſme which denominates an <hi>Anabaptist,</hi> ſeeme not to be fatall to the ſoule? To this I anſwer, that we muſt look how a doctrine is attended or conſequenced; the firſt circle in the water is the leaſt, thoſe that are cauſed by it are bigger and bigger, an opinion may be very ill as it is a baſtard miſ-begotten by miſ-inferences from the Word; but it is worſe as it is a whore and begets a new off-ſpring of errours more pernicious, but I muſt remember to whom I ſpeake. Brethren, if the ſheep be infected or worried, both God and men will aske, Where were the ſhepherds? or what did they in the meane time?</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the people I ſay but this, <hi>Rom. 16. 17. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you brethren marke them which cauſe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and differences contrary to the doctrine which yee have learned, and avoid them;</hi> The avoiding of ſuch teachers is your proper duty; as you would avoid an ambuſcado or ſtratagem of deceit: our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diviſions are ſcandalous to your ſelves, to your Miniſters, to the truth; for by reaſon of them, <hi>The way of truth is evill ſpoken of, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 2. they are the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111056:22"/> hopes of the common enemy, and our own weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and becauſe I have named the enemy, let no man thinke that the betraying of theſe differences among our ſelves doth give handle and occaſion to them, to traduce us all as Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, Sectaries: we need not feare the calumnies of thoſe to whom godlineſſe it ſelfe, as Chriſtianity of old, was crime enough, we ſhall doe our ſelves right in their eyes by diſclaiming them. The Apoſtles doe boldly tax the diviſions among Chriſtians not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any upbraidings of the Heathens. Let them ſay that we are about (inſtead of purging the Temple as Chriſt did<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) to ſet up a Pantheon (as the <hi>Romans</hi> did) or an Altar to the unknown god (as they of <hi>Athens</hi> did.) This water will not ſtick upon us long, they will be of another mind when we ſhall ſhake this viper off our hand; In the meane time I beſeech you to conſider whether beſide the ſleight and cunning craftineſſe of ſeducing teachers, there be not ſome other ſtratagems on foot, acted from behind the doore and at a greater diſtance, ſome hand of <hi>Ioab</hi> is in all this, the polititian and the Jeſuite blow theſe coales, they would make us as <hi>Samaritans</hi> and <hi>Iewes</hi> to one another. Let us not gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie our enemies. Ile ſay but this, obſerve the brand or character ſet upon the ſeduced, <hi>Vnſtable ſoules,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 14. <hi>ſilly women laden with ſins, led away with divers luſts,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 6, &amp;c. and upon the ſeducers, <hi>merchants of mens ſoules,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 3. <hi>unruly, vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talkers, deceivers, aiming at filthy lucre,</hi> Titus 1. 10, 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, lawleſſe perſons, 2 <hi>Pet. 3. 17. men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 8, &amp;c.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111056:22"/> but admit there be a face and preſence of holineſſe in the perſon, may we not then more ſecurely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their doctrine? To this I anſwer, that both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and doctrine may carry a faire ſtamp and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription. We doe not weigh gold to try the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it, but the weight. Guilded pills may convey poiſon. Satan in <hi>Peter</hi> is not eaſily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. The better paſſe that error brings with it, the more dangerous it is.</p>
            <p>So much upon the ſecond part of the text. The third is the preſervative or antidote againſt all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of ſuch teachers as come with ſleight and ſubtilty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that is two-fold, 1. The Miniſtery which Chriſt hath given to his Church, for this ver. relates to the 11. <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that henceforth,</hi> &amp;c. and to them doth the Apoſtle commit the charge of the flock, to watch over them againſt wolves, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 28, 29. 2. The holding faſt and purſuance of the ſubſtance and great things of Religion, ver. 15. <hi>but being ſincere in love grow up in all things into him which is the head:</hi> Its an excellent growth, to grow up into the head, that is, into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with and conformity to Jeſus Chriſt, which triviall opinions nothing at all advance; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>antitheſis</hi> or oppoſition he makes between being carried about, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and following the truth in love, for <hi>contraria, contrarijs,</hi> diſeaſes are cured by contraries; ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 17, 18. gives the ſame receipt againſt unſtedfaſtneſſe, <hi>but grow in grace and in the knowledge of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> and to take off teachers from fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and genealogies, and queſtions of no value;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111056:23"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> commends to them the aiming at <hi>godly edifying which is by faith,</hi> and to hold to that which is <hi>the end of the commandement, charity out of a pure heart and of a good conſcience and of faith unfained,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 4, 5. If both Miniſters and people would but drive this trade, it would take off that wandring and hunting after novell opinions and doctrines, and would keep us conſtant in the wholeſome paſtures, even now that the hedge of ſetled government is wanting; If you have good feeding, why ſhould not that keep you from wandering, untill the pale be ſet up, wait upon God in the uſe of his ſaving ordinances; and pray for us. If <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtay long in the mount, muſt the people be ſetting up golden calves, and ſay we know not what is become of this <hi>Moſes; Aarons</hi> rod ſhall ſwallow up all the rods of <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> in<note place="margin">Exod. 7. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> due time. The Apoſtle puts us in hope of a <hi>nil ultra</hi> to ſuch, 2 <hi>Tim. 3. 9. They ſhall proceed no further, for their folly ſhall be manifeſt unto all.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
